so now what I will show you next and this will
be discussed in several points during the course
is that writing multi-threaded
processes is challenging
writing code that can be
executed by multiple threads
puts a lot of pressure on programmers because
of several challenges you have some of them
here but before we look into these challenges we
need to understand the difference between parallel
execution and concurrent execution this is
extremely important parallelism implies that the system
can perform more than one task simultaneously
concurrency supports more than one task making
progress at the same time so the operating
system your computer together with operating
system can have several threads that are
making progress during a certain period of time
to show you what this means let's have a look
at this so here we have four threads in the
first case we have a single core and we see that
over time the four threads are all being executed
this is a concurrent execution if you freeze time
and you look inside the core you will find one
thread executing so running one line of code
from one process there is only one thread
at the time and so one process at the time that
is being executed the execution is concurrent
the execution of the different threads when we
talk about parallel execution on the other hand
we are talking about a system in which we have
multiple cores and at the same instant of time so
if we freeze time and we start looking inside the
cores we can find more than one instruction that
is being executed at the same time in this
case here you can see that thread 1 and thread 2
are being executed in parallel while here thread 1
and thread 2 are being executed concurrently
now when we have parallel execution of
multi-threaded processes we can go in two
ways usually one is to take advantage of
multiple threads to perform data parallelism
in this case we might for instance i
don't know look for an element inside an array
and instead of having one thread that
searches the entire array have two
threads each searching one half of the array in
this case it might be that two distinct threads
are actually running the same lines of code
from the same process and this I mentioned
in some video before multithreading doesn't
mean that you are executing different parts of
the process you might be executing the same
part but on different data an alternative to data
parallelism is task parallelism so in that case you
distribute different tasks to different threads so
you can have a thread checking for updates another
running the spell checker and another one printing
documents and so on if we go back to our example
about Microsoft Word as we will see CPUs
have cores as well as hardware threads
there is architectural support
for threading you have mechanisms
such as hyper trading and so on so
this I'm mentioning because as I said in the
beginning and I will repeat several times there
is a tight connection between the operating
system and the hardware that is designed
to be compatible and in line
with modern operating systems